今天有个特别的小礼物给大家
I have a special treat for y'all today.
我的好友兼以前同事
My dear friend and former college roommate is here
从休士顿的约翰逊航天中心来这里
from the Johnson Space Center in Houston
跟我们大家聊聊我国的太空计划
to talk to us about our space program.
是的  我知道你们都在想什么
And yeah, I know what you're thinking.
这两个人曾是室友
These guys were roomies.
怎么会一个就变成了...
How does one go on to be a....
太空总署的酷炫科学家
a fancy scientist at NASA,
而另一个人在教高一科学
and the other's teaching freshman science
而且还是在公立学校里教
at a public high school?
怎么了  谢尔顿
Yeah, Sheldon.
我刚才就在想这个
I was thinking that.
谢谢
Thank you.
好的  让我们用热烈的掌声
All right, uh, let's give a warm welcome
欢迎我的好兄弟  罗纳尔多·霍奇斯博士
to my good buddy, Dr. Ronald Hodges.
孩子们  大家好啊  很高兴来到这里
Hey, kids. Hey. Glad to be here.
回答一下休伯特你的问题
And, uh, Hubert, the answer to your question is,
其中一个室友忙着读书
one of those roomies was busy studying
而另一个室友忙着泡高中妹
while the other was out chasing high school girls.
是的
Yeah.
我澄清一下  那些姑娘都满18岁了
To be clear, they were all over 18.
这个嘛...
Yeah. Well...
来  我觉得今天可以聊的比较有趣的东西
Now, what I thought would be fun to talk about today
是太空总署除了太空梭之外的计划
is what NASA's planning on doing beyond the space shuttle.
比如首个上火星的载人航天任务
Things like the first manned mission to Mars.
你说
Uh, yeah.
你看了电影《异形》吗
Did you see the movie Aliens?
看了
I did.
你觉得那电影酷吗
Did you think it was cool?
算吧  我看得挺开心
Sure, I enjoyed it.
我也是
Me, too.
打橄榄球的吧
Football player, right?
是的  先生
Yes, sir.
好  但首先呢
Now, of course, before
在我们出发去探索太阳系之前
we can set out to explore the solar system,
有几个小问题我们得先克服
we've got a few minor problems to overcome.
比方说  首先呢  每一次发射
Not the least of which is, every time we launch,
都要花掉美国纳税人民
it costs the U.S. Taxpayers
上亿美元的税金
hundreds of millions of dollars.
别  别  别啊
Oh, no, no, no.
-你说  -如果你想省钱
- Yes. - If you want to save money,
为什么不把助推火箭降落回收
why don't you land the booster rockets
而是随它们降进大海里去呢
instead of letting them drop in the ocean?
这主意挺有意思
That's a cute idea,
但技术上来说不可能
but, uh, it's not technically possible.
为什么不可能
Why not?
这很难解释
Well, it's hard to explain.
这其中牵扯到很复杂的数学
The math is pretty complicated.
说不定我能帮你算算呢
Perhaps I could help you with it.
我相信你肯定行
Well, I bet you could.
你肯定行啦
I'll bet you could.
这样吧  这是个太空总署布贴
I'll tell you what. Here is a NASA patch.
带回家让你妈妈缝到你书包上吧
Why don't you have your mom sew that on your book bag?
有谁想要知道太空人怎么上厕所的
Now, who here wants to know how astronauts go to the bathroom?
-我  我想知道  -好
- Me. I do. - Oh, right.
其实呢  火箭升空时
See, now, during liftoff,
所有的太空人都穿尿布
all the astronauts wear diapers.
很多人常会寻思为什么
People often wonder why I chose
我选择进理论物理学这一领域
to pursue a career in theoretical physics.
我通常都会回答
I usually respond by saying
我想要揭开宇宙万物运转的核心奥秘
I wanted to unravel the inner workings of the universe.
所以或许当柯克舰长在剧里说"勇敢前进[大便]"
Yeah, perhaps when Captain Kirk said, "To boldly go,"
《星际旅行》系列中的名句"勇踏前人未至之境"
或许指的是勇敢拉一泡
he meant in one of those, huh?
但其实真实的原因是
But the real answer was
我想要证明这个猪头三错了
I wanted to prove this nincompoop wrong.
说不定剧里那句是"传送我吧  屎[史]考提"
Yeah, that's right. Beam me up, Potty!
♪ 世上没人比我强壮 ♪
♪ Nobody else is stronger than I am ♪
♪ 昨天我移了一座山 ♪
♪ Yesterday I moved a mountain ♪
♪ 我相信我能当你的英雄 ♪
♪ I bet I could be your hero ♪
♪ 我是个了不起的小家伙 ♪
♪ I am a mighty little man ♪
少
年
谢尔顿
我今天见了个律师
So I saw a lawyer today.
为什么
Why?
我在安排我的临终遗嘱
I'm putting together my last will and testament.
我们会想你的
We're gonna miss ya.
乔治
George.
没事  我屁都不会留给他
Don't worry. I ain't leaving him squat.
你要死了吗
Are you dyin'?
我们都会死啊  亲爱的
We're all dyin', honey.
从我们出生的那一刻起
From the second we're born,
就在慢慢滑向死亡的深渊
it's just a slip and slide into the darkness.
除非你被吸血鬼咬了
Unless you get bit by a vampire.
那个还用说吗
Well, now that goes without saying.
我不想死  我才亲过一个男生而已呢
I don't want to die. I've only kissed one boy so far.
什么
What?
别紧张  是很久以前的事了
Relax. It was a long time ago.
你放心了吗
Are you relaxed?
谢利  你晚饭一口都还没吃
Shelly, you haven't touched your dinner.
你没事吧
You feel okay?
没事  我只是在想事情
Oh, yes. I was just thinking.
想什么呢  宝贝
About what, baby?
可回收再利用的火箭的最佳高度与宽度比
The optimal height-to-width ratio for a reusable rocket.
我刚才也在想这件事呢
I was just thinking the exact same thing.
真的吗
Really?
小饼饼  我真是爱死你了
Oh, Moonpie, I love you so much.
很晚了  你不睡在干嘛
It's late. What are you doing up?
我正在做火箭回收降落时的双曲线计算
I'm working on the hyperbolic calculations for a rocket return.
需要帮忙吗
Need any help?
什么
What?
开玩笑的
I'm kiddin'.
关灯上床睡吧
Now, turn out the light and go to bed.
-可是...  -快去
- But... - Now.
爸爸  我们买得起电脑吗
Dad, can we afford a computer?
我的税务是你在弄的  你觉得呢
You do my taxes. What do you think?
那没事了
Never mind.
晚安
Good night.
姥姥
Meemaw?
小饼饼先生  有何能为你效劳
Mr. Moonpie, how might I help you?
您去世后准备留下多少钱给我
How much money are you planning to leave me when you die?
有缘再相会
Nice talkin' to you.
姥姥
Meemaw?
要重新修改你的用词吗
Want to try that again?
我想要买台电脑
I need to buy a computer
好解出纳维-斯托克斯方程
so I can solve the Navier-Stokes equation.
那一台电脑多少钱
Uh-huh. How much is a computer?
苹果有一台不错的要两千块
Apple has a nice one for $2,000,
但我需要的那种要三百万
but the kind I need costs three million.
让我看看我小金库里有多少钱
Let me see what I got in the vault.
9块钱外加...
Nine bucks and, uh...
瞧瞧  是墨西哥披索
Oh, look at that-- a peso.
还带着体温
It's warm.
您好  第一国家银行
Hello, First National Bank.
我想要跟一位信贷员谈谈
I'd like to speak with a loan officer.
是跟我家屋子的二次抵押有关
It's regarding a second mortgage on my home.
我的名字叫谢尔顿·李·库珀
My name is Sheldon Lee Cooper.
好  我可以等
Sure, I'll hold.
我讨厌死等待铃声了
Oh, I hate hold music.
你好
Hello.
是的  你能帮到我  桃乐丝·菲茨帕特里克
Yes, you can help me, Dorothy Fitzpatrick.
我有兴趣将房子二次抵押
I'm interested in taking out a second mortgage.
我9岁  为什么这么问
I'm nine years old. Why do you ask?
你这是年龄歧视  桃乐丝
That's called age discrimination, Dorothy,
但我大人不记小人过
but I'm willing to let it slide.
你觉得我可爱是好事  但我是认真的
I'm glad you find me cute, but I'm deadly serious.
我需要资金来买电脑
I need funds to buy a computer.
不  房子不是在我名下
No, the house isn't in my name.
我9岁  我们已经确认过这件事了
I'm nine. We've established this.
但我父母的税都是我在帮忙报的
I do prepare the taxes for my parents,
如果我们勒紧裤带
and if we tighten our belts,
抵押资产的净值足够我们申请贷款
we'll have sufficient equity for the loan.
谢尔顿你在跟谁说话
Sheldon, who are you talking to?
桃乐丝·菲茨帕特里克
Dorothy Fitzpatrick.
桃乐丝·菲茨帕特里克是谁
Who's Dorothy Fitzpatrick?
是你学校新认识的女同学吗
Is she a new buddy from school?
她是梅德福第一国家银行的信贷员
She's the loan officer at The First National Bank of Medford.
你为什么在跟她说话
Why are you talking to her?
妈  能等会儿在说吗
Mom, can this wait?
我在跟她谈有利条件呢
I'm trying to negotiate favorable terms.
还在吗  桃乐丝
Hello. Dorothy?
你怎么没去上数学课
Hey, how come you weren't in math class?
太空总署来的那个人把我当小孩对待
That guy from NASA treated me like a child,
我要证明他是错的
and I need to prove him wrong.
你就是个小孩啊
You are a child.
小心说话啊  朋友
Tread lightly, my friend.
英格拉姆女士有因为我翘课不高兴吗
Was Ms. Ingram upset I wasn't in class?
她其实挺高兴呢
Actually, she was happy.
她还手足舞蹈了一会儿
She even did a little dance.
你知道谁那里有路由器吗
Do you know anybody with a modem?
睿侠电器行应该有  怎么了
I think Radio Shack has one. Why?
我需要进约翰逊航天中心的
I need to access thrust-to-weight ratios
ftp服务器来得到推力重量比数据
from the FTP server at the Johnson Space Center.
之后呢
Then what?
给太空总署的那人看我的计算啊
Then I show that guy from NASA my work
然后嘲笑在我面前俯首称臣的他
and laugh as he begs for mercy.
有时候你说话像个邪恶魔王
You know, sometimes you sound like a super villain.
安静
Silence!
等你长大变声后再说会比较有用
That'll be more effective after your voice changes.
安静
Silence.
妈  你能带我去睿侠电器行吗
Mom, can you take me to Radio Shack?
今天不行
Not today, baby.
我得先去买菜然后开始做晚饭
I have to go food shopping and get dinner started.
但我有重要的事
But it's important.
对不起啦  等周末看看吧
Sorry. Maybe over the weekend.
但我用不了多少时间啊
But it won't take that long.
谢尔顿  我说了不行
Sheldon, I said no.
-妈  -不许再说
- But, Mom... - Not another word.
笑什么
What?
我穷开心不行吗
Can't I just be happy?
妈妈  拜托了
Mom, please!
谢尔顿·李  我说了不行
Sheldon Lee, I said no.
我还在开心呢
I'm still happy.
求你了  妈  你这样很不公平
Please, Mom! You're being unfair!
-还是不行  -但我真的很需要推重比数据
- No. - But I really need those thrust-to-weight ratios.
你没看到我在做饭吗
Do you see I'm cookin'?
那晚饭后带我去嘛
Well, take me after dinner.
别再说了  今晚我哪里都不会带你去
Enough! I'm not takin' you anywhere tonight.
我并不引以为豪
I'm not proud of it,
我小时候  曾经也...
but as a child, I was prone...
偶尔会气到爆炸
to the occasional meltdown.
香蕉你个大西瓜
Cheese and crackers!
抱歉让你听到这污言秽语
I'm sorry you had to hear that.
好啦  我终于把他安抚好了
All right, I finally got him calmed down.
你怎么做到的
How'd you manage that?
很简单  给他个拥抱再喂一点感冒糖浆
Easy. Gave him a hug and a little cough syrup.
妈
Mom!
他又不用操作重型机械  嗜睡没事的
It's not like he's operating heavy machinery.
我们不能让他这么闹下去
We can't keep putting up with this behavior.
-我们得禁足他  -怎么禁足
- We need to ground him. - How?
你跟他说"不许你出去玩了"
If you say "No playing outside,"
他会说"谢谢"
he says, "Thank you."
我们总得管教他吧
Well, we need to do something.
就是闹脾气嘛  孩子都会这样
It's just a tantrum. It's what kids do.
你以前整天处罚我啊
You used to punish me all the time.
那不一样  你当年就是欠揍
That was different. You were a pain in the ass.
要不一个月不许去睿侠电器行
I say no Radio Shack for at least a month.
我看行
Sounds fair.
我去跟他说吧
I'll go tell him.
要我就会等到明天再说
I'd wait and tell him tomorrow.
他现在有点昏沉
He's a little loopy right now.
晚安啦
Good night.
她用药弄晕了我们儿子
She drugged our son.
之后开始了我人生最漫长的一个月
Thus began the longest month of my life.
失去了得到推重比数据的能力
Without the ability to access the thrust-to-weight ratios,
我周密的羞辱太空总署科学家大计
my well-intended effort to humiliate a NASA scientist
受到了严重阻碍
ground to a halt.
妈
Mom.
怎么了
Uh... what's going on?
谢尔顿好像不舒服
Something's wrong with Sheldon.
怎么啦  儿子  肚子疼吗
What's the matter, baby? Have a tummy ache?
有可能是胃溃疡
I think it's an ulcer.
别犯傻了
Don't be silly.
-你肯定是吃错什么了  -才不是
- You must have eaten something. - No.
我的症状符合胃溃疡的病徴
My symptoms are consistent with an ulcer.
谢利  还记得你以为自己得了麻风病
Shelly, remember when you thought you had leprosy,
结果只是有块皮肤有点干吗
and it was just a patch of dry skin?
还有你以为自己得了痛风  或前列腺肿大
And when you thought you had gout? Or an enlarged prostate?
还有疯牛症
Or mad cow?
那次是我的最爱
That was my favorite.
这次真的不一样
Well, this is different.
或许我们该带他去看医生
Maybe we should take him to the doctor.
听你老婆的话啊  胃溃疡是很严重的
Listen to your wife-- ulcers are serious.
我从没在这么小的病人身上看到
Well, I've never seen this in someone so young,
但你儿子的确是得了胃溃疡
but, uh, your son has an ulcer.
谢谢
Thank you.
怎么会这样
How could this happen?
有好几个可能因素
Uh, there are a number of factors.
他最近有遭受什么特殊的压力吗
Has he been under some unusual stress lately?
有  她不带我去睿侠电器行
Yes. She won't take me to Radio Shack.
去外面等
Go wait outside.
我听过一些有趣的研究
I've heard some interesting research
说用抗菌剂可以治胃溃疡
about treating ulcers with antimicrobials.
出去
Go.
你还好意思惊讶我得胃溃疡
And you're surprised I have an ulcer.
我还惊讶我为什么没得呢
I'm surprised I don't have one.
睿侠电器行是怎么回事
Um, Radio Shack?
他想算出怎么帮忙太空总署回收火箭
He's trying to figure out how to help NASA land rockets.
这挺不错的啊
Oh. Well, that's a nice thing.
但他是为了报仇才这么做
He's just doing it out of spite.
好吧
Okay.
这段期间别让他吃辣的食物
Well, keep him off spicy foods for the time being,
我再给你开胃溃疡药的处方签
and I'll write you a prescription for Zantac.
他抽烟吗
Does he smoke?
当然不抽  他才9岁
'Course not. He's nine.
我在他这年纪就开始抽了
I started at his age.
但只有在我喝酒时才抽
Uh, but only when I drank.
什么...
What the...?
谢尔顿  你在干嘛
Sheldon! What are you doing?
给我一分钟就好  这玩意太慢了
I just need a minute. These things are so slow.
这是你的家人吗
Is this your family?
感觉人都好棒
They're lovely.
-妈妈  -怎么了
- Mom. - What?
谢尔顿又有毛病了
There's something wrong with Sheldon again.
我算出来了
I figured it out!
一晚
One night.
我就想好好睡一晚
I want to sleep one night.
妈  你来啦
Oh. Hi, Mom.
大家好
Hi there.
作文本
火箭重返大气层与反推进
由
谢尔顿·李·库珀著
1989年11月9号
♪ 我在路上  成功的路上 ♪
♪ I'm on my way, I'm making it... ♪
我的研究告一段落
With my research complete
胃溃疡也在好转中
and my ulcer on the mend,
剩下的就是把我的作品送到太空总署
all that was left to do was send my work to NASA
坐等成为美国科学界人见人爱小甜心
and wait to become America's scientific sweetheart.
♪ 我会从大门走入 ♪
♪ And I will walk through the front door ♪
Peter Gabriel -  Big time
♪ 发达 ♪
♪ Big time... ♪
于是我等呀等
So I waited...
♪ 得表现出来 ♪
♪  Make it show, yeah ♪
♪ 发达 ♪
♪ Big time. ♪
等呀等
...and waited...
♪ 发达 ♪
♪ Big time. ♪
等呀等
...and waited...
...and waited.
♪ 发达 ♪
♪ Big. ♪
谢尔顿又有毛病了
Something's wrong with Sheldon again.
又怎么了
Now what?
太空总署的那些人一直没给他的成果回信
Those people at NASA never responded to his science stuff.
靠  我真是受够了
Damn it. I've had enough of this.
谢尔顿  起来
Sheldon, get up.
起来有何意义
What's the point?
我们去休士顿
We're going to Houston.
真的吗
Really?
真的
Yeah.
你跟我一起去给这些太空猴子
You and me are gonna give those space monkeys
好好上一课
a little talkin' to.
我时常觉得我父亲
I often found my father to be
是个奇怪又令人不解的男人
a strange and puzzling man,
但在那一刻  我从未如此爱过他
but at that moment, I never loved him more.
为什么我不能待在家啊
I don't see why I couldn't stay home.
因为我们要来一次快乐家庭出游
'Cause we're having a fun family outin'.
好歹让我开车吧
Can I at least drive?
你妈是说快乐  不是快死
She said fun, not tragic.
我们去那个鸵鸟园吧
Let's go to the ostrich farm.
太酷了
Cool.
我们可以骑着它们遛几圈  再宰了吃
We can ride 'em, and then we can eat 'em.
我们哪儿都不停
We're not stopping anywhere.
直接去休斯顿把你弟弟的事儿整明白
We're going to Houston to straighten this thing out for your brother,
然后就回家
then we're going home.
谢利  你还好吧
Shelly, you doing okay?
还好  但愿我不会晕车
Yes. I just hope I don't get carsick.
想让爸爸停一会儿吗
You want Daddy to pull over?
我没事的
I'll be okay.
天啊  他吐到我鞋子上了  我的鞋上
Oh, God, it's on my shoes, it's on my shoes!
老天爷啊  谁来开个窗
For Pete's sake, somebody open a window.
我无意冒犯
Yeah, I don't mean to be rude,
不过我们等见你上司已经一小时了
but we've been waitin' for an hour to see your boss.
对不起  先生
I'm sorry, sir,
你们没有预约就来了
but you didn't have an appointment.
我们没有预约的原因是每次我打来
We didn't have an appointment 'cause every time I called,
你就会让我稍候
you put me on hold.
我确信霍奇斯博士会尽快见你们的
I'm sure Dr. Hodges'll see you as soon as he can.
-你打算怎么办  -我也不知道
- So, what do you want to do? - I don't know.
只能耐心等着...
I guess we just got to be patient and wait...
管他那么多
Aw, screw it!
抱歉  先生  你不能就这样...
Excuse me, sir, you can't just...
你给我听好了
All right, here's the deal.
我的孩子因为你患上了胃溃疡
My kid's got a damn ulcer 'cause of you,
所以你要么认真对待他
so either you take him seriously,
要么就想想怎么对付我
or you're gonna be taking me seriously.
请吩咐  先生
Yes, sir?
珍妮丝  不如请那位小伙子进来吧
Janice, why don't you send the little boy in?
快快有请
Right away.
他可以见你了
He'll see you now.
到你了  小饼饼
You're up, Moonpie.
在这个阶段
And here...
火箭靠近远地点时  利用万向节
near apogee, we gimbal the engine
驱动发动机施加转矩
to exert a torque
执行重力转向机动
that executes a pitchover maneuver
将火箭翻转180度
to flip the rocket by 180 degrees.
你的成果很了不起
Well, that's very impressive.
感谢你抽出时间...
Thank you very much for taking the time...
我还没讲完
I'm not done.
抱歉
Uh... sorry.
不用说
Needless to say,
我们必须使用比例-积分-微分控制器来尽量减少
we use a P.I.D. Controller to minimize the dispersions
着陆点的散布范围
to the landing site.
还有别的吗
Anything else?
有  我想喝水
Yes. I'd like a glass of water.
我该吃胃溃疡药了
It's time to take my Zantac.
他进去好一会儿了
He's been in there quite a while.
只要话题关乎科学
Well, if the topic is science,
他就是个小话唠
he can be a really Chatty Patty.
无聊死了
I'm bored.
我也觉得
Me, too.
未来会有人给谢尔顿写本书
Someday somebody's gonna write a book about Sheldon.
你们不想看到里面某个章节
Don't you want there to be a chapter
写你们俩是多有爱地支持他吗
about how loving and supportive you two were?
我无所谓  反正我也不会看
Doesn't matter. I ain't reading it.
你的成果极具开创性
This is groundbreaking work.
谢谢  还有呢
Thank you. And...?
还有什么
And...?
我以为你会想道歉
I thought you might want to apologize.
为什么要道歉
Why?
你想用一个布贴让我闭嘴
You tried to shut me up with a patch.
我...  我见人就送布贴
Well... I-I give those to everyone.
还有你得明白  谢尔顿
A-And you have to understand, Sheldon,
虽然你的计算在理论上是正确的
that while your math is-is theoretically correct,
但是我们没有技术能力来执行它
we don't have the technical capability to execute it.
所以我走在时代前头了吗
So I'm ahead of my time?
看来是这样
Well... it would appear so.
好吧  等你们水平赶上来再联系我
All right, call me when you catch up.
我们可以走了
We can go now.
我时常深思  如果那一天我父亲
I've often contemplated what might have happened
没有为我挺身而出  一切会变成什么样
if my father hadn't stuck up for me that day.
我会继续在科学道路上前行
Would I have gone on to become
成为世界级的理论物理学家
a world-class theoretical physicist,
还是那种平庸的蓝领理论物理学家
or just your average Joe Sixpack theoretical physicist?
爸爸
Dad?
怎么了
Yeah?
谢谢你
Thank you.
不用谢
You're welcome.
我们为你骄傲  亲爱的
We're real proud of you, honey.
-你们也为我和小乔治骄傲吗  -当然了
- Are you proud of me and Georgie? - Of course.
当然
You bet.
骄傲什么
For what?
见好就收吧
Don't go pokin' at it.
2016年4月8日
史上第一次
For the first time,
太空探索技术公司研发的"猎鹰9"火箭
SpaceX has successfully landed its Falcon 9 rocket
成功返回着陆于大西洋上的无人降落台
on a drone ship in the Atlantic Ocean.
其公司创始人埃隆·马斯克称这次着陆
SpaceX founder Elon Musk called the event
为"太空史上令人难以置信的里程碑"
an "Incredible milestone in the history of space."
埃隆  CNN记者到了
Elon, the CNN reporter's here to talk to you.
等等
Hang on.
请他进来
Send him in.